okay so this is episode two of my
youtube experiment and today what I want
to do is I wanted to talk about what I
have long thought is in fact one of the
most important concepts in the
contemporary environment and one of the
least talked about and least well
understood and this is the the
distinction between rival rest's Goods
arrivals phenomena and anti rivalries
phenomena I think this this concept by
itself if fully grasped may be the most
important one out there so on that note
let's start so the rival risk is pretty
straightforward it consists of things
like hamburgers and glasses of water and
oil where if I have it you don't have it
and if I have consumed it then it's gone
forever all right so these are
fundamentally not shareable and
fundamentally entropic kinds of things
and it's I think it's fair to say that
most if not all of our economic
structures and to a great extent many of
our legal and political structures for
say the past 15 thousand years have been
about trying to solve the problem of how
do we most effectively which sometimes
means most equitable and sometimes it
means most productively generate and
distribute rather loose goods right I
mean for most of human history the
problem of how do we feed people has
been the problem
contemporary or at least say late
seventies economical political
structures being the most effective
figured out thus far now the the anti
rival risk is very importantly
completely different in kind it is that
set of things where if I have it you can
also get a completely functional copy of
it without me losing it at all and
actually even more importantly the more
people who have it the more valuable it
becomes
you know the canonical example here
would be something like say language or
a telecommunications network like the
Internet you know if I'm the only person
who speaks Esperanto it's not worth
anything but if I teach you Esperanto
which has some cost but the cost of that
is is minuscule compared to the cost of
creating the language in the first place
it gets more violent of course every
additional person gets added to the
network increases the value of the
network exponentially arises this
Metcalfe's law and sort of a more
fundamental notion of what kinds of
things intrinsically participate in
Metcalfe's law okay so the first insight
once you have this distinction is to
recognize that a lot of the deep
concepts that we apply and use to make
good choices in the domain of the rival
risk actually don't work at all in the
domain of the antivirus for deep reasons
so for example let's take the micro
economic concepts supply and demand the
price function in a rival risk domain
where the cost of production is
asymptotically related in some fixed way
to the value meaning that even though
you can get more and more efficient and
say producing a car the production of a
car has some fixed relatively fixed cost
and as a consequence there is a point at
which it just doesn't make sense to make
more cars the incremental marginal value
of the new car
less than the incremental marginal value
started marginal cost of creating a new
car and this is good - characteristic
characteristic of all kinds of rivals
phenomena there's just a crossover point
where it costs too much to make more in
the relationship to the amount of value
that you can generate out of it and and
there seems to be an intrinsic
decreasing returns to scale so that any
in any given technological framework you
could squeeze a certain amount of
efficiency out of your production path
and then you reach an asymptotic limit
now of course we we can continually move
into new kinds of technological
frameworks and we'll speak about that in
a moment but once you're in one that's
where you're stuck and in this context
the price function actually ends up
being a perfectly efficient way of
identifying what is the appropriate
combination of where an individual
should point their attention meaning if
I want to figure out what I should do
all I have to do is look for the places
where I can make the most money if the
economy says that I make more money
being a elementary school teacher or
being a coal miner then that's what I
should do at least within the domains of
what microeconomics can accomplish and
also it serves as the mechanism for
motivation of that same behavior and so
if I want to buy stuff then I need money
and the way that I get money is by doing
the stuff that the economy says is a
value and so this is Orthodox economics
and at least within the domain of the
rival risk it more or less works I mean
there's a lot of fuzziness outside of
the notion of a perfect economy but it's
still a good good theory and the price
function is effective now the problem is
is that it doesn't work at all in the
antivirus and this is I think important
it's not that it doesn't work a little
bit we can kind of clued you to make it
work
it's actually the opposite direction so
for example we have tried to clear the
entire concept of intellectual property
the notion of creating rival ristmas to
creating scarcity around fundamentally
anti robbers things like ideas is our
effort to shoehorn the anti Rawal risk
into
rival wrist legal economic and political
frameworks so how do we tell people how
valuable it is to create new ideas well
if all we've got is supplying a minute
the price function we have to turn these
new ideas into the functional equivalent
of a barrel of oil into the functional
equivalent of a ham sandwich there's
only so much that can go around its
scarce and so the price function works
the problem is since the the marginal
cost of copying say something like
calculus is effectively de minimis it's
effectively zero and the marginal value
is not just the value that a nurse to
the individual who gets it right so
there if I don't know calculus is value
to me of me learning calculus but
there's also the Metcalfe's law which is
that calculus in general gets more
valuable to literally everyone the more
people who have it so what that means is
that to put a very fine point on it you
should be willing to pay me to learn
calculus at least some amount and in
fact as a community we should be
collectively willing to pay effectively
anyone to learn calculus because the the
net-net value to the whole to the
community is going up exponentially and
the marginal cost of learning it is in
fact asymptotically going down there's
some flat level and there's specific
reasons which has to do with the
relationship between the rival risk and
the anti rivalries I guess if you
followed me this far it might be worth
diving into that a little bit I
apologize that this is getting a bit
convoluted I don't have enough skills
and video to edit this this is all being
taken in one splurge
so we talked earlier about the notion of
the way that you might move from one
technical regime to another technical
regime and right now we're focused on
what are the actual limits of where the
answer driver is doesn't reduce to zero
copying costs and this is just where
those two pieces relate so the anti
rival risk is how we innovate and
develop new technical regimes so when a
given rival economy shifts to a new
fundamental capacity it does so on the
basis of some anti robbery's innovation
and somebody in events invents the wheel
somebody invents the steam engine
somebody invents electricity
which is an anti rivalries phenomenon to
change the underlying basis upon which
the entire robbery's economy operates
and so that's one side of it innovation
waves are the anti rivalry is feeding
back on the rivalries
contrariwise the amount of irreducible
energy that is necessary for a copy of
the anti rather is to be written to a an
agent is the the rival hrus constraining
the the effectiveness or the propagation
of the anti robber so you know if it
takes a human being say a year to learn
Chinese then the amount of actual
rivalries energy of feeding that
individual housing that individual and
maintaining the integrity of their
intention and the opportunity cost of
doing just that is the rivalry substrate
against which the antivirus is working
ok so now we get to the last point why
is this the crown jewel well you might
be able to get so the the anti rivalries
is the crown jewel because of this
exponential it is the thing that causes
the exponential to show up at all that
once you've developed once one person
has done the work of developing calculus
it is almost free for everyone else
which means that the next group of
people who are coming don't have to
reinvent calculus they just learn it and
then they get to use it and then they
get to innovate on top of it so rather
than constantly investing most of your
energy and merely reproducing a constant
state every iteration of generativity is
building on a effectively free existing
state and this of course is what
generates Exponential's now if you take
that fact and you combine it with the
recognition that our entire social
economic and legal infrastructure is
currently optimized for the rival risk
see the opportunity if we can figure out
how to construct a social framework
which is optimized for the anti-rattle
risk you should expect to see a rather
dramatic increase in anti rivalries
generation and of course when you're on
an exponential any increase is a massive
increase in any shift to the right if
you could move like imagine if you were
able to teleport your portion of society
to 2025 next year so everybody else is
at nineteen twenty nineteen and you're
at twenty twenty-five in terms of
comparative technological capability
well that's a decisive strategic
advantage I mean you just have
exponentially more capability than
people who didn't make that move so an
appropriately designed anti rival rest's
civilization toolkit reaches escape
velocity visa vie the sum total of all
rival risks civilizations that's it
that's the key idea